Marie F. and James S. Peters II Papers 2002.0062
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Marie F. and James S. Peters II Papers
undated, 1948-2005.
2002.0062
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
5.2 Linear feet
The collection contains the professional papers of Marie Ferguson Peters, the first African American Professor at the University (Home Economics, 1963), and her husband, psychologist James S. Peters II. Drafts and proofs of Dr. James Peters' work is also included in the collection.
Peters, James S., II.
Peters, Marie Ferguson.
Biography
Marie Ferguson Peters was born in Lincoln, Nebraska on 9 April 1918. She graduated as valedictorian from Tuskeegee Institute High School in 1934 and attended Fisk University (A.B., Chemistry, 1938), Atlanta University (M.A., Chemstry, 1941), Purdue University (M.S., Sociology, 1955) as well as graduate work in sociual work at the University of Chicago and her Ph.D from Harvard University in 1976. Prior to her employment at the University of Connecticut in 1963 as a part time instructor on the Hartford and Torrington campuses, Ms. Peters was an instructor at Virginia State College (1942-1945); editor at Science Research Associates (1950-1956); sociologist for the Hartford Neighborhood Centers (1957-1958); writer, for educational consultants Glick and Loren (1959-1961); and instructor at the University of Hartford (1961-1963). Peters transferred to the Storrs campus of UConn in 1966 as an Assistant Professor in the School of Home Economics.
James Sedalia Peters, II, was born on 11 May 1917, on his grandmother's farm in Ashdown, AR. The son of Edward Walter Lee Peters and Ardell Peters Merrit (Duckett), he grew up in Monroe, LA. After graduating from Southern University, where he was captain of the football team and a T.H. Harris Fellow, he taught high school in Natchitoches, LA. He came to Hartford in 1940 to attend the Hartford Seminary. During World War II, Peters served in the Navy at the Great Lakes Naval Training Center. After the war he lived in Chicago, where he worked as a counselor for the Veterans Administration and pursued graduate studies in psychology at the University of Chicago and the Illinois Institute of Technology. After receiving a fellowship from the VA, he completed his doctorate at Purdue University in 1954. He was the first African American to receive a faculty appointment at Springfield College. In 1957, he was appointed director of the State of Connecticut's vocational rehabilitation program. He and his family moved to Hartford that year and to Avon in 1960. In Avon, he served on the Republican Town Committee. After his wife received a faculty appointment at the University of Connecticut, the family moved to Storrs in 1976. In 1982, Dr. Peters retired from the State as Deputy Commissioner of Education and established a private practice in psychology in Windsor. He was adjunct faculty at the University of Hartford for many years, served in that capacity at the University of Connecticut, and was a visiting distinguished professor of rehabilitation at Southern Illinois University. He was a commissioner of the Hartford Housing Authority and served on the boards of American School for the Deaf, the Hartt School of Music, the Greater Hartford Urban League, which he helped to found, and the Greater Hartford YMCA. He served on the vestry of Trinity Episcopal Church, Hartford. He was a member of Rotary International, Civitan, Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, and Sigma Pi Phi Boule. Dr. Peters was especially proud that his research was used to help support the racial integration of the Navy and that he was inducted into the first class of the Connecticut Veterans Hall of Fame by Governor M. Jodi Rell. Dr. James Peters passed away 12 December 2008.
Scope and Content
The collection contains primarily the professional papers associated with the careers of Marie F. and James S. Peters II, in their respective areas of specialization. Dr. James Peters wrote several books later in his life, as well as his memoirs, which are also represented in the collection.
Arrangement
The collection has not been arranged and the inventory represents materials as they were separated from the monographs that were also donated at the same time.
Series I: Inventory ( undated, 1948-2005 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Dodd
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in two parts, the first by Dr. James Peters in 2002 and the remainder by the executor of the estate in 2009.
Peters, James S. (James Sedalia), 1917-; Peters, Marie F.; Correspondence.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Oral Histories.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Publications.; Typescripts.
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1948-2005
  - undated, 1958-2005 (Box 1)
    - The Saga of Black Navy Veterans of World War II: An American Triumph mss, undated
    - Papers of JSP, Part I-II mss, 1955-1988
    - Filling in the Gaps: A Memoir proofs, undated
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Chapter 1-7 notes, undated
    - "Social Justice for the Disabled,", undated
    - Vocational Rehabilitation Administrative Study, undated
    - Essays on Rehabilitation, undated
    - Paraloma Homecoming, 2005
    - "History of Beta Sigma Boule of Springfield, MA, 1983-1991,", undated
    - Spirit of David Walker, undated
    - Dream Worthy to be believed, undated
    - Comprehensive Statewide Planning for Vocational Rehabilitation Services, v. I-II, IV, undated
    - Vocational Rehabilitation of the Disabled and disadvantaged in the US and Europe, undated
    - Socio-Egocentrism. Theory, Research and Practice, undated
    - Memories, undated
    - Story of Joe Toth, undated
    - Study of the psychological and social problems of Negro migrants in Hartford and its vicinity, undated
  - undated, 1955-1988 (Box 2)
    - Papers of JSP, Part II mss, 1955-1988
    - Study of the Wechsler-Bellevue verbal scores of negro and white males (MS thesis), undated
    - Spirit of David Walker, undated
    - Essays of JSP, 1957-1988
    - Books by JSP, undated
    - Correspondence with publisher, undated
    - Fliers, undated
    - Drafts, undated
    - Clippings, undated
    - Notes for Memoirs, undated
    - Biographical materials, undated
    - Syllabi, undated
    - Examiner manual for Socio-Egocentrism, undated
    - Oral History of Dr. E.T. Dunlap, undated
    - Her Eyes have seen the glory, undated
    - Nine Black Families, 1976
    - MFP articles and publications, undated
    - "Investigation of attitudes of Purdue University students toward woman's roles," MFP MS thesis, undated
  - undated, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Nine Black Families (MFP dissertation) Investigation of attitudes of Middlebury College students towards women's roles, (D-MP BA thesis), 1975
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Clippings, undated
    - MFP published work, undated
    - Socio-Economic Egocentrism in Delinquents and non-delinquents, undated
    - Vocational Rehabilitation Administrative Study, undated
    - "A Dream worthy to be believed,", undated
    - "Study of the Psychological and social problems of negro migrants in Hartford and its vicinity" (MA JSP), undated
    - Division of vocational rehabilitation--a dynamic organization, undated
    - Study of the Wechsler-Bellevue Verbal scores of Negro and White males, undated
    - Assessing Outcomes in Child and Youth programs, undated
    - Preliminary investigation of positive and negative reactions to 10 middle-middle class negro mothers, using the thematic apperception test, undated
    - Papers of JSP, v. 1-II, undated
    - Report of the Committee on Human Rights, undated
    - Vocational rehabilitation and disability determination, undated
  - undated (Box 4)
    - Photographs, undated
    - Southern Illinois University, undated
    - Socio-egocentrism, undated
    - Grant to Cerebral Palsy Association, undated
    - Monroe Colored High School reunion, undated
    - Independent Social Center, undated
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Camp Bennett, undated
    - William S. Peters--A forgotten hero, undated
    - Truth Award, undated
    - "Travails and achievements of a Black Southern New Englander,", undated
    - Memoirs of a Black Southern New Englander, undated
    - MFP lecture series, undated
    - Family Studies news, undated
    - UConn, undated
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Index cards, undated
    - Gavel, undated